Togame!
とがめ
大丈夫か
Are you okay?
とがめ　とがめ
Togame!
Togame!!
Togame! Stay with me!
とがめ　しっかりしろとがめ
とがめ　とがめ
Togame!!
Togame! Togame! Togame!
とがめ とがめ とがめ
Togame!!
Seitou
Hakari
Scales,
the True
The army general director in support of critical tasks under direct control of Yanari Shogun of the Owari Shogunate, Togame the Strategian.
尾張幕府家鳴将軍 直轄預奉所軍所総監督　奇策士とがめが
何やら不思議な現象に遭っているのは　今から３日前
The strange task she is performing started three days ago,
when she and the 7th generation Kyotouryuu head Yasuri Shichika arrived here at Hyakkeijou in Oushuu,
虚刀流七代目当主 鑢七花と共にここ奥州百刑場にて
and met the 10th sword Seitou Hakari's owner, Higaki Rinne.
１０本目の　「誠刀·銓」の所有者
彼我木輪廻に会ってからでございます
Oushuu - Hyakkeijou
Three
days ago
Hyakkeijou.
百刑場
This is where everyone in Hida Takahito's rebellion was publicly executed.
それは 飛騨鷹比等はじめ 反乱にかかわった者が
皆処刑された公開処刑場であり
２人にとって因縁の場所なのでございます
It is a land of fate for these two.
何だろう
What is this...
胸が痛え
My chest hurts...
締め付けられるような
Like I'm being squeezed or something.
自分の大事なものが失われたような
It feels like something important to me is being trampled.
踏みにじられたような気がする
Togame!
とがめ
I never imagined that my homeland would be in such a state when I finally came back to visit.
まさか こんな形で故郷を訪れることになろうとは
思っておらんかったがな
Good grief...
やれやれだ
なあ　本当にこんな所に仙人がいるのか
Hey, is there really a holy man living in a place like this?
どう見ても人が住んでいる様子はないぜ
It doesn't look like anyone can survive here.
Should we go check out the nearby towns?
これから手当たり次第近くの村を当たっていくってことなのか
No, that won't be necessary.
いや　その必要はない
Higaki Rinne is here, just hidden from us.
彼我木輪廻は　ここにいる
ただ　姿を現さぬだけでな
What do you mea—
何を言って
Why is there a girl here?
どうしてこんな所に女の子が
Oh?
へえ　君には僕がそういうふうに見えるのかい
Is that how I appear to you?
女の子になるのは久しぶりだな
It's been a while since I was a girl.
I guess I'll have some fun.
まあ　堪能させてもらうさ
Well anyway, pleased to meet you.
そういうわけで初めまして
僕は彼我木輪廻だよ
I am Higaki Rinne.
Pleased to make your acquaintance.
今後よろしくお見知りおきをってところかな
あんたが彼我木輪廻 仙人の
You're Higaki Rinne?
The holy man?
Indeed I am.
いかにも
Yo, Togame-chan.
やあ　とがめちゃん
Yep, you don't even have to say it.
言わなくても分かっているよ
You're after Seitou Hakari, correct?
「誠刀·銓」が　欲しいんだろう
そうかい　そうかい
I see, I see.
Sure, I'll hand it over.
いいよ　あげる
It's buried over there, so go ahead and dig it up.
そこに埋めてあるから好きなように掘り出しなさい
It's probably about 30 meters underground.
たぶん　１０丈くらいの深さかな
However, you'll have to do it yourself, Togame-chan.
もちろん　君１人でやってよね とがめちゃん
It's right underneath where you're standing.
ちょうど　君の立っている真下だから
Well, have fun!
まっ　頑張ってみてよね
He disappeared...
消えた
Togame! Are you okay?
とがめ　大丈夫か
It's morning already?
もう　朝か
Don't overdo it.
無茶すんなよ
今日ぐらい休めって
Just rest for today!
I can't do that.
そういうわけにはいかぬ
I have to dig 30 meters by myself.
１人で１０丈掘らねばならぬのでな
ていうか奇策はどうしたんだよ
Whatever happened to your schemes?
いつものとがめなら奇策を練って彼我木と交渉するだろ
Normally you'd have come up with some plan to negotiate with Higaki.
会いたくない
I don't want to see him.
Even since finding Higaki Rinne, you've been acting really strange.
彼我木輪廻に会ってから
とがめは絶対変だ
It's hard for me to just watch you being cornered like that.
追い詰められているっていうか
そんなとがめ俺見てられねえよ
なら　見るな
Then don't watch!
彼我木輪廻か
Higaki Rinne, huh...
What's wrong, Yasuri-kun?
どうかしたのかい　鑢君
Togame-chan is in her own little world digging, huh?
とがめちゃんは今日も穴掘りに夢中かな
あんたが１０丈の深さに銓を埋めたせいでな
Because you went and buried Hakari 30 meters underground.
Why did you bury Seitou Hakari?
どうして「誠刀·銓」を埋めたんだ
It was just a hassle.
あんな刀邪魔なだけだからね
And throwing away something that a friend gave me would be kind of rude, so...
かといって友人としてもらったものを捨てるのもなんだし
It was just the most convenient way.
つまり埋めるのが一番　よかったんだ
You got it from a friend?
友人からもらった
Yeah.
そうだよ
From Shikizaki Kiki himself.
四季崎記紀　本人からね
四季崎記紀からうん
From Shikizaki Kiki?!
Yep.
「うん」って
Wait, how old are you??
あんたいったい何歳だよ
Around 300 years?
およそ３００歳
人間だったころを含めれば３５０歳かな
350 if you include the time I was human.
Have we met somewhere before?
あんた俺とどっかで会ったことないか
Nope.
ないよ
僕はこれでも仙人だからね
I'm a holy man here, after all.
基本的に俗世からは離れている
I fundamentally avoid things of the world.
でも　俺はあんたを知っているような気がする
But I sort of feel like I know you...
それはね君がこの僕をそういうふうに見ているというだけなんだよ
That's because of how you're seeing me.
What you're seeing is a projection of your memory.
僕はね君の記憶の投影なんだ
記憶の投影
Projection of my memory?
Right, a true perception based on your true memories.
そ　君の正当なる記憶に基づく正当なる認識だ
誇りにこけるまでもなくね
Hakari doesn't have anything to do with it.
People look past my own existence and see a perception of their own memories.
人は僕という存在を通して自分の記憶を覗くことになるのさ
Even with me here, we don't really exist.
僕は居ながらにしてこの世に存在していない
That's what a holy man is.
それが仙人ということだ
I don't really understand you...
よく分からねえな
What exactly is a holy man?
一体仙人って何なんだ
そうだね　一言で言えば
Well, in a word, a holy man is something like a mirror to people.
仙人は人にとって鏡みたいなもんだよ
鏡
A mirror?
Yeah.
あ　真実を映し出す魔法の鏡ってところかな
A magic mirror that reflects the truth.
鑢君　こんな外国の童話を知っているかな
Yasuri-kun, have you heard of this foreign fairytale?
何だよ
What?
In a far off land, there lived a queen.
とわる所に女王様がいてさ
そんな女王様が鏡に対して聞くわけだよ
She had a mirror that she always asked,
鏡よ鏡　鏡さん
"Mirror, mirror on the wall, who is the fairest one of all?"
この世に一番美しのは誰と
女王様としてはここで自分だっと答えて欲しだけれど
The queen wanted the mirror to say it was her, but it would reply with the name of another whom she hated.
鏡は女王様が大嫌いな違う人物の名前を答えるんだ
What do you think, Yasuri-kun?
けどさ鑢君　これってどう思う
Should the mirror have given that answer?
鏡がそうな事答えると思うかい
思うも思わねいも　鏡がしゃべるわけねいだろ
It's not like a mirror can talk in the first place!
Exactly.
そう
答えのは　鏡じゃない
It wasn't the mirror answering, but rather the queen's true feelings responding to her vanity.
女王様自身の心根が
自身の虚栄心に対してそう言ったにすぎないだ
If what you say is true then everything just becomes what you want to see.
あんたの話だと 全部見る側の都合みてえだな
A holy man doesn't do anything.
仙人は何もしないんだ
Or rather, cannot do anything.
というよりも　何もできない
何かしでかすのはいつも君ら人間なんだよ
It's you humans who actually carry out tasks.
Doesn't anything come to mind when I say that?
そう言われて思い当たる節はないかいこの僕の姿に
The instant you saw me, you gave me this form.
君が僕を見た瞬間に形成されたこの僕の存在に
Itezora Konayuki...
凍空こなゆき
Nee-chan...
姉ちゃん
汽口慚愧か
Kiguchi Zanki?
Tsuruga Meisai...
敦賀迷彩
Itezora Konayuki, Nee-chan, Kiguchi Zanki, and Tsuruga Meisai, huh?
凍空こなゆき
姉ちゃん
汽口慚愧
それに敦賀迷彩ね
I lost to those three.
俺は　この３人に負けたことがある
３人
Three?
敦賀迷彩には負けちゃいねえが
I didn't lose to Tsuruga Meisai, but...
かなり苦い経験みたいだね
Sounds like it was a harsh experience.
後悔と罪悪感だろ
You feel regret and guilt, right?
Yasuri-kun, looking at your own memories is recognizing the parts of you that you don't want to face.
鑢君自分の記憶をのぞくとは
自分の苦手意識をのぞくということだよ
People change their memories to suit what they're most comfortable with.
自分の記憶っていうのはたいていの揚合都合よく改変されてるからね
However, that doesn't work with me.
しかしこの僕を通してしまえばそうはいかない
It seems I've failed.
どうやら僕は失敗してしまったようだよ
At this point I've conveyed to you all that I needed to, so we'll part here.
こうやって最後に君に伝えるべきことを伝えられたんだから
それでよしとしよう
When you're with me, you will have to face your darkest memories whether you want to or not.
僕といると
いや応なしに苦手な思い出したくもない己の記憶と向き合うことになるのさ
Yasuri-kun.
鑢君
人知を超えた仙人たる僕の見るところ
From the perspective of a holy man beyond human understanding...
君はここらでそろそろ自分の苦手意識と向き合うことが必要だろう
You too will have to face the darkness you avoid.
The 12 Maniwa Corps heads has been reduced to just two.
真庭忍軍十二頭領もたった２人になってしまったというわけだ
ど　どうしましょう鳳凰さま
W-What should we do, Houou-sama?
There's nothing we can do.
どうしようもない
With the loss of Oshidori, we have no choice but to continue on with our plan.
鴛鴦１人　欠けたところで
いまさら計画を変更するわけにもいくまい
このままわれらは奥州を目指す
We will head for Oushuu.
それにあの男がいつ現れるか　分からないのでな
Additionally, we don't know when that man will make his appearance.
な　何者だったんでしょう
W-Who is he, I wonder?
I believe he's a subordinate of Princess Hitei.
否定姫の配下だと　われは読む
Princess Hitei...
ひ　否定姫
Houou-sama...
ほ　鳳鳳さま
Yes?
ひょっとしてあの男の正体に心当たりがおありでしょうか
Might you have any idea of who that man actually is?
The way you've been talking about him, it sounds like you know him from long ago...
この間からの鳳凰さまの言いようを聞いていると
まるであの男のことを古くから知っているかのようで
You're pretty sharp.
鋭いなお前は
I have an idea, but I'm sure I'm mistaken.
心当たりがあるだけだ
おそらくはわれの勘違いだろう
か　勘違い
M-Mistaken?
Right.
そうだ あの男が生きているはずはないのだ
There's no way he could still be alive, or that he'd be working under Princess Hitei.
まして否定姫の下などで働いているわけもない
He was a ninja of pride and respect.
あれは誇り高き　忍者だった
This was before you were even born.
お前の生まれる前の話だよ
N-Ninja?!
に　忍者
Was he your friend?
お友達だったのですか
Like I said, it can't be him.
だからあの男ではない
あの男はすでに死んだのだ
That man died long ago.
There aren't any ninja left who hold their head high, us included.
誇り高き忍者はこの時代には生きていない
われらも含めてな
人鳥　もしも奇策士との交渉に成功し
Pengin...
If we succeed at the negotiations with the strategian and manage to get all the Perfected Deviant Blades, we'll be retiring from active duty.
われらが完成形変体刀を全て手にすることができたなら
われも現役の引き時だろう
十二頭領を１０人も失った責任はわれが取らねばなるまい
And I must bear the responsibility for losing 10 of the 12 heads.
I will entrust the future of the clan to the next generation.
次の世代へと希望を託すことにしよう
ご　ご冗談を
Y-You're joking...
It's no joke.
冗談ではないさ
どころか　われの跡を継ぐのはお前しかおらんと思っているよ人鳥
In fact, the only one left to hold the torch after I'm gone will be you, Pengin.
結局のところ　時代の遺物なのだ
I am but a relic of the previous generation,
奇策士も虚刀流も否定姫も
along with the strategian and Kyotouryuu and Princess Hitei...
そして四季崎記紀の完成形変体刀も
And also, Shikizaki Kiki's Perfected Deviant Blades.
鳳凰さま
Houou-sama...
さて　道行きを急ぐとしよう
Now then, let us hurry.
あの　洋装仮面の男がいつ襲撃してくるかも分からん
That masked man may attack at any time.
そ　そうですね
I... I see.
やあ　鑢君
Yo, Yasuri-kun.
You look bored.
暇そうだね
Becoming weaker when wielding a sword is almost like a curse.
剣を取った方が弱くなるなどまるで　呪いのようですね
呪い
Curse?
The day after winning Outou Nokogiri
Shinou Issou Dojo
Kyotouryuu: Bellflower!
虚刀流　桔梗
Bellflower
Ow...
痛てててて
さすがですね
Impressive.
もう少しの間はごまかせるかと思ったのですが
I thought I'd be able to keep up the act for a bit longer, but this is my limit.
これが限界です
It's my loss, Shichika-dono.
参りました　七花殿
どうでしょう
What do you think?
I believe I may have shone some light on your troubles.
七花殿のお悩みに
何らかの風穴は開けられたのではないかと自負いたしますが
I don't really get it...
いや　よく分からねえんだけど
わたしが言いたいのは「一芸に秀でる者は万芸に秀でる」ということです
What I'm saying is "To excel at an art is to excel at versatility".
Even for an amateur such as myself,
初心者のわたしでも
戦えと言われれば　ある程度の徒手空拳の振る舞いは可能なのです
I can still put up some semblance of a fight.
You're saying it's strange that I'd get weaker by holding a training sword?
つまり木刀を持ったことであそこまで弱くなるのはおかしいってことだよな
ですから　わたしは「呪い」という言葉を使ってしまった
That's why I used the word "curse".
This is just my intuition as a swordsman, but in the same way that the Shinou Issou school holds certain tenets at its core,
これは剣士としてのわたしの勘ですが
心王一鞘流が心王一鞘流であるために必要な概念が幾つかあるように
your Kyotouryuu may also have certain core concepts that make it what it is.
七花殿の虚刀流が虚刀流であるために
必要な概念があるのかもしれません
Nee-chan!
姉ちゃん
わたしは刀だわ
I am a sword.
あなたも刀
As are you.
Shichika...
七花
My little brother...
わたしの弟
You finally killed me.
わたしをやっと殺してくれる
ヤダ
No!
I... I...
俺は
Is this what happens when a sword tries to use a sword?
刀が刀を使おうとするとこうなってしまう
The complete inability to wield a sword is the nature of Kyotouryuu.
刀に関する才能を　一切持たぬ
それが　虚刀流
姉ちゃん
Nee-chan!!
刀が刀を使っちゃいけねえ
A sword can't use a sword...
それがあんたの言う虚刀流の呪いなんだな
Is that the "curse" of Kyotouryuu?
Congratulations, Yasuri-kun!
おめでとう鑢君
It seems you understand now.
何か分かったみたいだねえ
Good job!
ホントによかったねえ
There's one thing I want to ask.
一つ　気になってんだけど
何だい
What's that?
あんたの姿や中身は
You said that your appearance and behavior are a projection from my memories, right?
「見る側の記憶の投影だ」って言ってたよな
そのとおり
Exactly.
Then who did you get that arrogant personality from?
じゃあ　その人を食った性格ってのは誰なんだ
Ah, that comes from how Togame-chan sees me.
ああこれは　とがめちゃんにとって
僕は　そういう人だってことだよ
あんた　とがめの記憶からも形成されているのか
You've taken a form from Togame's memories?
そうだよ
Yep.
君らは２人で一緒に　僕を見たからね
Because you two saw me at the same time.
My appearance and behavior are from your memories, and this personality is from hers.
姿や　立ち居振る舞いは君の記憶から
この性格は彼女の記憶からのようだね
So even Togame has something she's weak against?
あの　とがめに苦手なもんなんかあるのかよ
苦手なものを
Everyone has something difficult to deal with, or that they don't want to remember.
思い出したくもない記憶を持たないものなんていないよ
Something Togame finds difficult to deal with?
とがめの苦手なやつ
Hida Takahito!
飛騨鷹比等
ひ　飛騨鷹比等
Hida Takahito?
Yes, that personality is exactly like my father.
あやつの性格はわたしの父親にうり二つだ
That pompous manner of speech, those antics, that cavalier attitude...
あのもったいぶったしゃべり方
ふざけた態度
砕けた態度
何よりわたしに肉体労働を強いるというこの嫌がらせ
And to top it all, forcing me to do physical labor.
It's exactly the sort of thing that guy would do!
わたしが最も苦手としたあの男がいかにもやりそうなことなのだよ
そ　そうか
I-I see...
己の苦手意識と向き合えか
Recognize the parts of yourself that you don't want to face...
どうりでここへ来てからというものあの男のことを思い出すわけだ
It's true that my father is what came to mind upon returning here.
In his dying breath, he told me something.
いまわの際に父がわたしに何かを言い残したようなのだよ
For me to have forgotten something so important...
そんな大切なことすら忘れていた
I guess that unpleasant woman is with Higaki Rinne around now...
今ごろあの不愉快な女は彼我木輪廻に会っているのかしらね
Owari Castle grounds
Princess Hitei's Palace
Higaki Rinne the holy man?
仙人の彼我木輪廻ですか
しかしよりによってあの仙人に「誠刀·銓」を託すとは
Though, to entrust Seitou Hakari to that holy man of all people...
That's very much like something you'd do.
姫さまもずいぶんなまねをなさいますね
I wonder if he's there to get in the strategian's way?
いつもの奇策士に対する嫌がらせなのでしょうか
勘違いしないでよ
Don't be mistaken here...
別にわたしが彼我木輪廻に託したわけじゃないわ
It's not like I'm the one who gave it to Higaki Rinne.
In fact, it's a bother for me as well that he has it.
むしろあいつが所有しているせいで困ってるくらいなんだから
More importantly, what happened with Dokutou Mekki?
それより「毒刀·鍍」
The most poisonous of Shikizaki Kiki's Deviant Blades, Dokutou Mekki...
四季崎記紀の作りし変体刀の中でも最も強い毒を持つ鍍
For you to have failed at assassinating Maniwa Houou and let him run off with it...
それがよりにもよってあんたが暗殺し損ねた真庭鳳凰の手にあるとはねー
I am dishonored.
面目しだいもございません
Dokutou Mekki in the hands of Maniwa Houou...
「毒刀·鍍」と真庭鳳凰との組み合わせね
I honestly have no idea if this'll bring misfortune or catastrophe.
果たして凶と出るか大凶と出るか
わたしにも予想がつかないわ
But if the strategian does manage to get a hold of Seitou Hakari,
しかしもしも奇策士が「誠刀·銓」の収集に成功すれば
これでいよいよ四季崎記紀の作りし完成形変体刀十二本が全て
the stage will finally be set for all of Shikizaki Kiki's 12 Perfected Deviant Blades to be assembled.
舞台の上に出揃うということになるのですね
姫さまの悲願の達成も近い
The fulfillment of your ultimate desire is at hand.
Stop, stop.
ちょっと　ちょっと
I don't know who might be listening, so refrain from saying anything careless.
どこで誰が聞いているか分からないんだから
うかつなことを言うのはやめてちょうだい
そんな言い方をしたら
The way you put it, it almost sounds like I'm the descendant of the legendary swordsmith Shikizaki Kiki who ruled over the Sengoku era,
まるでわたしが伝説の刀かじ
戦国を実質的に支配した四季崎記紀の末裔で
and that I've have kept track of the Perfected Deviant Blades and stayed one step ahead of that unpleasant woman to collect them.
だからこそ完成形変体刀について色々と詳しく
あの不愉快な女に対して一歩先んじることができているみたいじゃない
That's totally not true of course, so there's no need to say it.
そんな事実はないんだからそんなことを言うべきじゃないわ
Indeed.
そうでしたもちろん姫さまは四季崎記紀の末孫などではございません
And of course, you are by no means Shikizaki Kiki's descendant.
My apologies for saying something that might cause a misunderstanding.
誤解を招くような発言をして申し訳ありませんでした
That's right, I am Princess Hitei.
そう　わたしは否定姫よ
I deny anything of myself outside of that.
それ以外の自分をわたしは余すところなく否定する
わたしの悲願なんて達成されようが達成されまいが
Whether I achieve my desire or not, I still deny it.
それこそ否定的なだけよ
Also...
それから
気になっていることがあってさ
Something has been bothering me.
これはついででいいからあんたが直々に調べてみてくれない
You don't have to do it now, but could you look into something for me?
何でしょう
What might that be?
この間奇策士と虚刀流をこの部屋に呼び付けたときのことなんだけどさ
I called the strategian and Kyotouryuu here not long ago...
After I told them where Seitou Hakari was, Shichika-kun seemed kind of strange...
「誠刀·銓」の在りかを教えた後の七花君の様子が何か変だったのよね
10 days ago
Seitou Hakari is somewhere around Hyakkeijou in Oushuu.
「誠刀·銓」の在りかは奥州の百刑場
Its owner is the holy man Higaki Rinne.
所有者は仙人の彼我木輪廻よ
What about the strategian?
奇策士の様子は
Unpleasant as always.
あの不愉快な女はいつもどおりよ
Come to think of it, that's her first time in Oushuu isn't it?
そういえばあの女も奥州は初めてなのよね
I wonder why?
何でかしら
She's part of the army, so wouldn't she be familiar with that area?
あそこは軍所の人間ならまず知っておくべき土地柄なんじゃない
まっ気のせいかもしれないけれど
Well, it might just be my imagination, but I don't mind the idea of sending you out on a wild goose chase either.
あんたに無駄足を踏ませるというのも悪くないわ
鑢七花と百刑場の関係
The relationship between Yasuri Shichika and Hyakkeijou...
あるいは奇策士とがめと百刑場の関係
Or maybe it's something to do with the strategian?
よろしく調べておいてちょうだい
Go find out for me.
御意
As you wish.
尾張幕府におります２人の鬼女
The two demonesses of the Owari Shogunate.
Real names unknown, history unknown—
Princess Hitei and the strategian Togame.
本名不詳経歴不明の否定姫と奇策士とがめ
The day of their showdown is fast approaching.
その２人の決着もそう遠くない日に迫っていたのでございます
What?
何
彼我木輪廻が四季崎記紀本人から「誠刀·銓」をまらっただと
Higaki Rinne received Seitou Hakari from Shikizaki Kiki himself?
友人として　もらったって言ってたな
He said he got it as a friend.
How could you forget to tell me something as important as that?
そんな　大事なことを言い忘れるとは
そなたどういうつもりだ
Well, I just told you...
どういうってだから　今　とがめに
ほかに言い忘れておることはないだろうな
Is there anything else you forgot to tell me?
あるならさっさと言え
Hurry and and say so if there is!
He said you've forgotten something important.
とがめは大事なことを忘れているって
それは自分の苦手意識と向き合わないことには思い出せないって
And if you don't face the part of you that you're avoiding, you'll never remember.
言い忘れたことはそれだけだと思う
I think that's everything I forgot to say.
そうか
I see.
So, do you intend to fight with Higaki?
それでそなた彼我木と戦うつもりなのか
ただ戦うだけなんて意味のないことしたいとは思わないけど
I can't imagine myself fighting him for no particular reason, but...
けど
But?
何のために戦うって聞かれたら戦わないわけにはいかないだろう
If you asked me why I fight, I'd say I have to fight.
その答えを見つけるためにさ
So I can find the answer to that.
You're pretty straightforward, as always.
相変わらず真っすぐだなそなたは
If you do find the answer to that, tell me.
七花　その答え見つけたならわたしにも教えてくれ
I'd love to know.
ぜひ聞きたいものだ
分かった
Okay.
Feel free to fight him.
存分にやり合うがよいわ
It'll be a good experience for you to go toe to toe with a holy man.
仙人と戦ったという経験は
そなたにとってかなり有益なものとなるだろう
Yeah.
Just to let you know ahead of time, I am way weaker than you.
先に言っておくけど僕は君よりも圧倒的に弱い
What, you're already making excuses for losing?
何だよ最初から負けたときの言い訳か
That's not it.
違うよ
君は自分よりも弱いものに勝てない
You can't win against people weaker than you.
That's what I mean.
そう言いたいんだよ
Shall we start then?
さあ　始めようか
いつでもおいで何て言って僕から掛かっていったりして
Come whenever. Or just watch me go first!
Kyotouryuu:
虚刀流　百合
Lily!
Kyotouryuu
Lily
He got me!
やられる
何
What?
虚刀流　薔薇
Kyotouryuu: Rose!
Kyotouryuu    Rose
おっと　危ない
Whoop, that's no good.
You're not getting away!
逃がすか
変だ
This is weird!
今までのどの戦いとも違う
It's different from any of my fights up till now...
I can't land anything on him!
かみ合わねんだ　このままじゃらちが明かねぇ
We're going nowhere at this rate!
虚刀流　七花八裂
Kyotouryuu: Shichika Hachiretsu!
Shichika Hachiretsu
Whoop!
て　てめえ　ずるいぞ
Damn it, that's unfair!
あんた　まさか
Wait, are you...
こいつ　戦おうとしてねぇ
This guy's not fighting at all!
自分から誘っておいて
He made the first move, yet he doesn't have any intention of fighting!
戦う気がまったくねぇんだ
You've forgotten something important.
とがめは大事なことを忘れている
And if you don't face the part of you that you're avoiding,
それは　自分の苦手意識と向き合わないことには思い出せないって
you'll never remember.
It seems I've failed.
どうやら　僕は失敗してしまったようだよ
What do you think history is?
君は歴史とは何だと思う
I think that history is the proof that humans lived.
僕はね歴史とは「人間の生きた証し」だと思う
The proof that humans lived to their utmost.
精いっぱい生きた人間の証しだと
That's why it looks and is the way it should be.
だからあるべき姿であるべきなんだと
And yet, this history is very different from how it should have been.
それなのに
この歴史は本来あるべき歴史とまるで違う
I spent much time trying to correct those errors.
僕はその間違いをじゅうぶんに示せただろう
And for now, my role here is over.
ここでひとまず僕の役割は終わりだ
At this point I've conveyed to you all that I needed to, so we'll part here.
こうやって最後に
君に伝えるべきことを伝えられたんだからそれでよしとしよう
Hide yourself here for a while.
君はこのままここに隠れていなさい
Do not come out under any circumstances.
絶対に出てきたら駄目だよ
もしも歴史が僕の思っているとおりなら
If history goes according to how I imagine, you will not die.
君だけは死なないはずだ
You will be the sole survivor in this cruel history to come.
君はこの過酷な歴史に生き残ることになる
The samurai code says I should kill you, but even for the sake of correcting history, that is one thing I cannot do.
武士道に従うなら
僕はここで君を殺してあげなきゃならないんだろうけど
いくらそれが歴史の間違いを正すために必要なことであっても
それだけはできない
自分の娘は
I cannot possibly kill my own daughter.
殺せない
Yo.
やあ やっぱり僕を殺しに来たのは君だったかい六枝君
So the one who came to kill me was you after all, Mutsue-kun.
僕は君のことが
I ... you...
That's... That's enough!
もう　もう　たくさんだ
なぜ　今になってこんなことを思い出させるのだ
Why are you making me remember this now?
君の戦闘能力を１０とすれば
If your fighting strength is 10, mine would be around 7.
僕の戦闘能力は７がいいところだろう
In a straight-up fight, I wouldn't even be a match.
まともにやり合ったら戦いにさえならないさ
That's why, by this point you should be torn into pieces!
だったら
今ごろあんたは八つ裂きになっているはずだろうが
However, your 10 strength is divided between offense and defense.
でもね君は１０の力を攻撃と防御に半分ずつ使っているんだよ
So basically, your attacking strength is only 5.
つまり攻撃において君の力は５割しか発揮されない
And so when I transfer all my strength into defense, your attacks cannot penetrate it.
僕の戦闘能力を全て防御へ回せば
君にはその防御を打破することはできないというわけだ
「誠刀·銓」という完成形変体刀の特性に従って言わせてもらうなら
If I had to name Seitou Hakari's focus as a Deviant Blade,
Note: True defense
I'd call it "Seitou Bouei".
「誠刀防衛」
Seitou Bouei
What exactly does Seitou Hakari's focus do?
「誠刀·銓」の特性って　何だよ
It's the most true sword in the world.
この世で　最も誠実な刀だ
I'm its owner after all.
何せ　この僕が所有しているんだからね
Like hell!
ふざけんなお前のどこが誠実なんだ
What part of you is "true"?
Come on, it's not fair to judge me like that.
おいおいそんなところを責めるなよ
My current personality comes from Togame-chan, remember?
この性格はとがめちゃんのせいだろう
Dammit, why am I putting up with this?
くそっ　やってられっか
This isn't even a fight!
こんなもん戦いでも何でもねえ
What's so fun about giving me more memories I'd rather avoid?
俺に新たな苦手意識植え付けて何が楽しいんだよ
楽しいよ～僕は嫌がらせが大好きなんだ
It's fun.
I love harassing people.
Even for this fight, you should be able to learn something.
こんな戦いでも人によっては得難き教訓を得られるはずなんだぜ
戦いなどむなしい勝ち負けに大した意味なんてないとね
"Fighting is futile".
"There's no meaning to victory or defeat".
とがめちゃんは「有益な経験になるだろう」なんて言ったみたいだけれど
Togame-chan said it would be a good experience for you,
but any experience you get from fighting is pointless.
戦いから得る経験なんて無益なもんだ
Any experience you'd get would only be unhappy.
有益であったとしても悲しいだけだ
君は彼女と１年近く戦ってきたわけだが
You've been fighting close by her for a year, but you don't seem to have learned anything from it.
まるでそれを学んでいなかったらしいからね
As kind-hearted as I am, I don't even feel like teaching you anymore.
親切な僕としては教えてあげたくなっちゃったのさ
大きなお世話だ
I don't need your help.
She takes fighting too far.
彼女は戦いにこだわり過ぎだ
It's almost like the concept of life itself is a fight for her.
何というか生きること自体が戦いといったふうじゃないか
What could her objective be?
彼女の目的っていったい何なんだろうね
君はそれを知っているけれどそれに同調しているわけじゃない
You may know it, but you don't see eye to eye.
You just sympathize with her.
同情しているだけだ
違う　俺は
No! I—
—fell for her?
ほれてる
けどさあ僕の見るところ君の気持ちは恋でもなければ愛でもないんだよねえ
But the way I see it, your feelings aren't anything like that of love.
聞き捨てならねえな
I can't let that one go.
そう　怒るなよ
Don't get angry now.
I'm sure you can calm yourself enough to listen.
このぐらいのことは聞き流さなくっちゃあ
僕はとがめちゃんの目的が何なのかは知らないけれど
I have no idea what Togame-chan's objective is, but I can tell you it's not something worth sacrificing herself for, much less others.
それが自分をましてや他人を犠牲にするほどのものじゃないことは
僕にも分かる
You must have realized that you've killed no small number of people over the course of your journey, right?
君だって刀集めの旅の途中で決して少なくない人数を殺しているんだろう
Robbing people of their greatest purpose—life itself.
生きるという人間にとっての最大の目的を阻害して 違うかい
Am I wrong?
Yasuri-kun, it's all over when you die.
鑢君 人は殺したら死ぬんだよ
You two have been ignoring such a simple principle.
君たちはそんな単純な原理からさえ目をそらしている
From my perspective, you, and of course Togame-chan, lack resolve.
僕から見れば君はもちろんとがめちゃんも
覚悟が足りない
"Hakari" means "scales".
「銓」ってのは「てんびん」って意味だ
君は自分のやっていることがどれほどの何と釣り合うのか考えてみることだ
You need to consider what you're doing and how it relates to everything around you.
Could you tell that to Togame-chan too?
とがめちゃんにもそう伝えてくれるかい
She probably won't talk to me.
彼女は僕と話してはくれないだろうからね
Sure, I'll tell her next time she takes a break.
次の休憩時間にでも伝えておくよ
That would be right now.
だったら　それは今だ
Seems she got tired and decided to take a break inside the hole.
とがめちゃん穴の中で力尽きちゃって休憩中みたいだからさ
とがめ
Togame!
What...
Why do you fight?
君は何のために戦う
Why do you fight so far as to sacrifice me?
わたしの命を犠牲にして君は何のために戦う
決まっているだろう
That's obvious.
とがめのためだ
For Togame, of course.
That's right...
そうだ　俺はとがめのために戦っているんだ
I'm fighting for Togame!
とがめと出会ったその日から俺は
From the day I met Togame, I...
The way I see it, your feelings aren't anything like that of love.
僕の見るところ君の気持ちは恋でもなければ愛でもないんだよねえ
Forget love or anything!
恋とか愛なんてくだらねえ
I fight for Togame!
俺はとがめだから戦っている
If it weren't for her, I wouldn't fight at all!
とがめでなければ戦ってこなかったってことだ
Got it, Higaki Rinne?!
分かったか彼我木輪廻
Togame!
とがめ　しっかりしろ
Hang in there!
とがめ　とがめ
Togame! Togame!
Shichirin...
しちりん　七花
Shichika?
大丈夫か
Are you okay?
彼我木輪廻との試合はどうだった
How was your fight with Higaki Rinne?
It wasn't really a fight.
それが勝負にならなくてよ
All he did was run.
あいつ逃げてばっかでさ
Run?
逃げる
「誠刀防衛」とか言って
He called it Seitou Bouei or something.
All his strength became defensive.
力の全てを防御に回すんだと
Isn't that running from a fight?
それあ　勝負放棄では　ないのか
けどよそれも１つの手なんだよな
Well, that's one way to do it.
勝負ってのは互いの合意で成り立ってんだから
A fight is an agreement between two parties, so if your opponent abandons the fight, you can't win.
相手が勝負を放棄しちまえば
勝つことができなくなっちまう
そうでもないぞ
That's not true!
その戦略には大きな穴がある
There's a big problem with that strategy.
If we can take advantage of that, we can defeat him!
その穴を突けば打破することができるだろう
What is it then?
なら教えてくれよ
I totally don't know what to do against a guy who can't lose.
負けてもねえのに負けたみてえで参ってんだ
Come on, think about it yourself a bit.
まったく　少し自分で考えろ
Obviously...
それはだなあ
I see...
そうか　そういうことか
So that's it...
僕は君のことが　大好きだった
I love you very much.
Shichika...
七花 わたしは父の最後の言葉を思い出したぞ
I remember what my father's dying words were...
よかったな
That's good to hear.
「誠刀·銓」で間違いないな
This is Seitou Hakari, no mistaking it.
You found it faster than I thought.
思ったよりも早く見つけたね
Well, you did present that strange riddle through Shichika.
七花を通してあれだけ謎掛けを持ち掛けられてはな
But you realized something, right?
でも何か気付きがあったんだろう
君が攻撃に重きを置いたままで発掘を続けていたら
If you had kept your offensive mindset while continuing to dig, would you have thought that hilt and blade was Seitou Hakari?
そんな　つかと　つばだけの刀を
「誠刀·銓」だと思ったかな
I probably wouldn't have.
思わなかっただろうな
「誠刀·銓」とは己自身を測る刀
Seitou Hakari is a sword upon which you weigh yourself.
人を斬る刀ではなく
It's not a sword that cuts people.
己を斬る刀
It is a sword that cuts oneself, tests oneself, and knows oneself.
己を試す刀
己を知る刀
だから　やいばなき刀
That is why it is bladeless.
You could say it is swordless.
無刀ということだ
ご名答
Well done!
考えてみれば分かりそうなものだ
It makes sense if you think about it.
A Japanese sword is not something you can safely preserve underground.
日本刀を地中に埋めて保管などできるわけがないからな
保管すべき　やいばがないのならば何の問題もない
But if it doesn't have a blade to preserve, then there's no problem.
I'm not really a fan of that way of reverse thinking.
そういう　答えから逆算するみたいな考え方 好きじゃないなあ
But I guess that's just like you.
でもまあそれはそれで君らしいか
That annoying personality is exactly like that man.
そういう　いやらしい性格
あの男に　そっくりだ
あの男が誰なのかよかったら教えてくれないかな
Who is "that man"? Mind telling me?
He's my...
わたしの父だ
...father.
I can't tell you his name though.
名は明かせぬがな
I see.
そうかい　嫌な父親だったんだね
Sounds like you didn't like him.
Were you hostile to him?
もしかして敵対でもしていたのかい
敵対などとんでもないわ
Completely the opposite.
In fact, I live for the sake of my father.
むしろわたしは父のために生きておるのだ
You could even say this sword collection is for his sake.
刀集めも父のために行っておると言ってよい
けど苦手だ
But you're uncomfortable with him.
Because you admitted that, you found Hakari.
君はそれを認めたから銓を発見できたんだし
And despite avoiding you, you stand before me now.
避けていた僕の前にこうして姿を現したんだろう
I wonder though, why didn't Yasuri-kun try to have another go at me?
でもさあ
どうして鑢君をもう一度けしかけてこなかったの
君なら僕に勝つ方法をすぐ思い付いたろうに
I'm sure you could figure out a way to defeat me.
If Shichika used all his combat strength on defense, what would happen?
七花の戦闘能力の１０を
全て防御に回したとしたらどうなる
You wouldn't even have a fight, never mind a match.
そうすれば　勝負どころか戦闘そのものが起こらない
So basically, by abandoning offense, even without winning, the result will be effectively victory.
つまり　攻撃を放棄することにより
勝ちではなくとも
結果的に勝利と同じものを得られることもあるということだ
続けて
Continue.
刀の本体はあくまでやいば
The essence of a sword is its blade, something that doesn't bend or break, and cuts well.
折れず曲がらずよく斬れる
That's what I had always thought...
それのみにあるとわたしは考えていた
しかしやいばがないのなら
But without a blade, you don't even need a sheath to protect it.
それを守るためのさやもいらぬ
If you can hold it with resolve, all you need are its hilt and guard to be able to face yourself.
こうして決意とともに握り己自身と向き合える
つかとつばのみがあればよい
That's what it means.
そういうことであろう
Precisely!
ご名答
Good job discerning that.
それに　ご明察だ
You're pretty smart, Togame-chan!
お利口さんだね　とがめちゃん
Having someone with the body of a little girl patronizing me like that really annoys me.
少女の姿で上から物を言われるのは
思いのほか腹が立つものだな
Higaki, as a reward for figuring it out, will you answer one question of mine?
彼我木よ　正解のご褒美に１つ
わたしの質問に答えてはくれぬか
Sure, I'll answer as many as you want.
いいよ１つと言わずいくらでも
You said you received Seitou Hakari from Shikizaki Kiki himself.
四季崎記紀本人から「誠刀·銓」を引き受けたということだったが
四季崎とはどのような男だったのだ
What kind of man was he?
I guess he was a denying kind of guy.
何ていうか
否定的なやつだったよ
否定的
Denying?
I feel like I've heard that somewhere before...
どこかで聞いたような言葉だな
Well, I said I was a friend, but it's been so long that I've forgotten quite a bit.
まあ　友人とは言ったもののかなり昔のことだし
結構　忘れちゃったけれど
But apparently he saw the profoundness of himself in me.
ただ　彼は僕の中に己の深遠を見たみたいなんだよね
で　とうとう　その苦手を苦手のまま
And eventually, he denied what he didn't want to face, and left.
否定したままに去っていったよ
僕に「誠刀·銓」を押し付けてさ
Not before pushing Seitou Hakari onto me though.
He was endlessly troublesome.
まったく迷惑極まりないよ
I really didn't want to get poisoned by it, so I buried it pretty quick.
僕はそんなものに毒されるのはまっぴらだから　すぐに埋めたのさ
埋めたのは最近の話ではないのか
Wait, so it wasn't recently that you buried it?
いや　もらった直後だよあっ
Nope, I did that right after I got it.
そしたらその上に城は建っちゃうわ
And then they built a castle on top of it, and then that castle burned down, and then they turned it into an execution ground...
その城が燃えたと思ったら今度は処刑場になっちゃうわ
The eras sure fly by.
時代ってのは流れるもんだね
I see...
そうか
飛騨城が存在する以前から
Seitou Hakari was buried here before Hida Castle was even built...
「誠刀·銓」はその下に埋まっていたのか
だから　父は気付いたのだ
So that's how my father saw the distortion of history.
歴史のゆがみに
そして　間違った歴史を正すために尾張幕府に弓を引いたのだ
And then to correct that history he drew his bow against the Owari Shogunate...
And then made the ultimate sacrifice.
多くの犠牲を払って
身内も味方も全ての命を危険にさらして弓を引いた
He put all his friends and family on the line to draw that bow.
歴史のために
All for the sake of history...
その辺りになってくると四季崎記紀の変体刀作りも
Around that time, he must have felt that the completion of the forging of Shikizaki Kiki's Deviant Blades was almost at hand.
だいぶ完了に近づいたって感じだね
Completion?
完了
変な言い方をするな
Don't say such weird things.
完成形変体刀はもう完成しておるだろ
The "Perfected" Deviant Blades have already been perfected.
Huh?
あれ
まさか知らないまま鑢君を引き連れているのかい
Don't tell me you've been taking Yasuri-kun along with you all this time without even knowing?
どういう意味だ
What do you mean?
How shocking....
これは驚いたな
完成形変体刀　十二本という習作を経て
How could you not know that after crafting the 12 Perfected Deviant Blades,
最後の最後に作られた完了形変体刀「虚刀·鑢」のことを
he went on to forge his final and ultimate
Completed Deviant Blade, "Kyotou Yasuri"?
何も知らないでいるとはまるっきり予想外だ
S-Shichika is one of Shikizaki Kiki's swords?!
し　七花が　四季崎記紀の刀
Not Yasuri-kun precisely, but rather Kyotouryuu.
鑢君がっていうか　虚刀流がだね
So that's why Sabi Hakuhei referred to him as a relic of Shikizaki Kiki?
だから錆白兵は虚刀流を差して「四季崎記紀の遺品」と言ったのか
He said Shichika was of Kiki's bloodline, and that Sabi himself was a failed creation...
記紀の血統だとそして
自分は失敗作だと
うーん　「血統」っていうか
Well, it's not so much "bloodline" as "swordline".
Bloodline
「血刀」なんだけどね
Swordline
It's true that Shikizaki Kiki and the Kyotouryuu founder Yasuri Kazune were from the same generation...
確か四季崎記紀と虚刀流開祖の鑢一根は
同世代だったな
So that means there was some connection between the two?
２人に何らかのつながりがあったということなのか
Was Shikizaki Kiki involved in the formation of Kyotouryuu?
虚刀流の成り立ちに四季崎記紀は関与しているのか
Completed Deviant Blade Kyotou Yasuri...
完了形変体刀「虚刀·鑢」
だから　無刀というわけか
That's why they're swordless?
Anyway, I'm taking Seitou Hakari.
ともかく「誠刀·銓」確かに　ちょうだいした
I learned a lot.
勉強になったよ
貴様のような戦術もあるのだと
I've come to understand your strategy of forcing a match to a draw by neither winning nor losing, all for the sake of your objective.
目的のためには
引き分けという不完全燃焼でさえのみ込まねばならぬということだな
Precisely... not quite right there.
ご名答じゃないね
それだけは
目的のために目的も捨てねばならない
You must throw away objectives for the sake of your objective.
それが今回君が得るべき教訓だ
That's the lesson you needed to learn.
Ambition, aspirations, vengeance...
野望も野心も復讐心も
You must throw aside all these objectives for the sake of your true objective.
真の目的のためには捨てるべき目的だよ
I understand that much.
それだけは得心しかねるな
目的以外のものは全て捨てられるが
I can throw away everything but my objective.
目的だけは捨てることはできない
Even after conquering what you couldn't face before, you still retain that stubborn streak.
苦手意識を克服してもその意固地さは変わらないか
Well, whatever.
まあいいさ それが　君の生きざまなら
If that's the way you live then you can just force your way through it.
貫き通してみればいい
ところで　お父さんの最期の言葉って何だったの
By the way, what were your father's last words?
That's obvious.
決まっておろう
父親が娘に向ける言葉だぞ
The words of a father to his daughter.
まして　わたしのようなかわいらしい娘にだ
Especially considering how cute a daughter I was.
だから　何だよもったいぶらずに教えてよ
So what was it?
Just tell me!
"I love you very much."
「僕は　君のことが大好きだった」
I didn't think I'd be able to say that.
こっちは　こんなに苦手に思っておったというのにな
俺が四季崎記紀の作りし変体刀の一本ね
So I'm one of the Deviant Blades that Shikizaki Kiki made, huh?
全然ぴんとこないな
I totally don't feel it at all.
Well to be precise, the Completed Deviant Blade isn't you yourself, but rather Kyotouryuu.
正確にはそなた個人が完了形変体刀なのではなく
虚刀流がなのだがな
開祖の鑢一根やそなたの父親である鑢六枝
The founder Yasuri Kazune, your father Yasuri Mutsue,
and even your sister Yasuri Nanami were all the Completed Deviant Blade "Kyotou Yasuri".
鑢七実もまた完了形変体刀「虚刀·鑢」ということになるのだろう
やっぱりだから　どうしたって感じだよ
I guess I feel it doesn't change anything.
Kind of like, "who cares?"
別に　どうでもいいじゃんみたいな
You're pretty easygoing.
気楽でよいなそなたは
You should bear some troubles in mind at least.
少しは悩むことを覚えろ
Well, I guess that's fine too.
まあ　それもまたよいのか
でもよ俺が刀剣を使えねえのって
So maybe the fact that I can't use swords is the curse that Shikizaki Kiki bestowed.
もしかしたら四季崎記紀のかけた呪いなのかもしれねえな
そうかもしれぬな
Possibly.
Either way, there are only two left, right?
何にしろ　あと残り２本か
Your dream is almost within reach.
とがめの野望もいよいよ終局ってわけだな
Don't get ahead of yourself.
まだ　何とも言えんよ
「毒刀·鍍」と「炎刀·銃」については何の情報もないのだからな
We don't know anything at all about Dokutou Mekki or Entou Jyuu.
それに
Also...
野望だの目的だの言うと
When you talk about "dreams" or "objectives", I feel like that holy man's going to appear out of nowhere again.
また　あの仙人が現れるかもしれぬのでな
You really aren't good at dealing with him, are you?
とがめ　相当　苦手なんだな
もう二度と会いたくないわ
I don't ever want to meet him again!
笑い過ぎだぞ　七花
It's not that funny!
Dewa
We're already at Dewa, huh...
もう　出羽か
Since we're here, why don't we pass through the Shougi town on the way back?
せっかくだから将棋村に寄ってから帰るか
どうして寄る必要がある
Why do we have to do that?
汽口慚愧に会うためか
So you can see Kiguchi Zanki?
Huh?
あーんって
What do mean "huh"?
ちぇりお
Cheerio!!
あんたの嫉妬深さは異常だ
Your jealous streak is really weird.
尾張にさっさと帰らねばならぬから将棋村には寄らぬぞ
We have to get back to Owari as fast as possible, so we can't go through the Shougi town!
とがめのためだ
For your sake.
何
What?
俺はとがめのために戦っている
I'm fighting for your sake.
That's the answer I gave.
それが俺の出した答えだ
とがめ　あれ
Togame, what's that?
Hey...
Is he alive?
生きてるのか
It's a sword wound.
刀傷だな
おっ　こいつは
This is...
た　助けて 助けてください
H-Help...
Please help...
It doesn't matter what happens to me...
ぼ　僕のことなんてど　どうでもいいから鳳凰さまを助けてください
But please save Houou-sama...
The strategian and the Maniwa Corps.
奇策士と真庭忍軍
時に協力し時に反目した彼らの因縁が
They have allied, they have fought.
ついに終焉の時を迎えようとしていたのでございます
But the final hour of their destiny together has arrived.
刀語 今月こよいの　お楽しみはここまでにございます
The story of Katanagatari on this month and this evening ends here.
shira nu
I don't know
shira nu furi de
Pretending to know nothing
unazuka nai
I don't nod
ina mu
I deny it
ina mu kokoro
My heart that denies it
oikake nai
I don't chase
maane utsushiyo wa yume
Maybe this world is a dream
de sou kashira
And, is that true?
iwa nu kika nu towa zu
I don't say I don't listen I don't ask
tashikame nai
I don't check
mie nu hate nu nige zu
It's invisible, it's endless, it doesn't escape
kawara nai kaware nai
It's unchanging, it's unchangeable
watashi wa mirai no subete makimodosou to shinai wa
I won't try to rewind all of the future
知らぬ知らぬふりで
kirai na koto dake mate ri
Only things I hate are waiting
頷かない
soba ni aru nante
Those are beside me
否む否む心
ina ina
Nay Nay
hitei hitei hitei hitei
Deny deny deny deny
追いかけない
me no mae no kako
The past in front of me
雨　映しようは夢ってそうかしら
wa ina mu
I deny it
There are only two swords left!
否む否む問わず
It's all going as planned, of course.
確かめない
I get kind of sad when I think this journey is about to end.
胸に残って逃げず
No, even after gathering the swords, life will still be complicated for Togame-san.
変わらない　変われない
This isn't the time to get distracted, Shichika.
私は未来の全て　巻き戻そうとしない
I'll do my best! I won't lose to myself!
With that said, next time on Katanagatari: Dokutou Mekki.
Cheerio!
Dokutou
Mekki
否否　この場でだけに側にいるなんで
If you're feeling down: one more Cheerio!
否否　否定否定否定
目の前の葛藤 はきだす